Guide to the Montana Department of Natural Resources, Water Resources Division records 1938-1971
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Natural Resources, Water Resources Division Records
1938-1971
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 431
Montana. Department of Natural Resources
.4 linear feet of shelf space
A sampling of Water Resources Division’s (1938-1971) survey books of various water related projects around the state, including dams, ditches, reservoirs, city water supplies, and pumping projects.
"Helping to ensure that Montana's land and water resources provide benefits for present and future generations" is the mission of the Montana Department of Natural Resources and Conservation (DNRC). First established in 1971 as a result of the Executive Reorganization Act of 1971, the DNRC provides leadership in managing the state's natural resources. It is presently responsible for promoting the stewardship of Montana's water, soil, forest, and rangeland resources; for regulating forest practices and oil and gas exploration and production.
Nine boards and commissions are attached to the department. Six of them—the Board of Land Commissioners, Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission, Board of Oil and Gas Conservation, Board of Water Well Contractors, Flathead Basin Commission, and Montana Grass Conservation Commission—have decision-making authority. The other three—the Resource Conservation Advisory Council, Rangeland Resources Committee, and Drought Advisory Committee—act in an advisory capacity only.
The department is organized into seven divisions: Director's Office, Conservation and Resource Development Division (CARDD), Forestry, Oil and Gas Conservation, Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission, Trust Land Management, and Water Resources. Two of the divisions—the Oil and Gas Conservation Division and the Reserved Water Rights Compact Commission—are attached to the department for administrative purposes only.
The Water Resources Division promotes and coordinates the beneficial use, conservation, protection and development of Montana’s water resources.
The Division carries out its duties for the purpose of promoting the general welfare and prosperity of the people of Montana. Sound coordination of the development and utilization of the state’s waters allows the Division to protect existing uses and to promote adequate future supplies for domestic, industrial, agricultural, recreation, the conservation of water for wildlife, aquatic life and other beneficial uses.
The Water Resources Division is responsible for many programs associated with the uses, development and protection of Montana's water. It manages and maintains the state-owned dams, reservoirs, and canals. The division also develops and recommends in state, interstate, and international water policy to the director, Governor, and legislature. The division consists of eight regional offices and five bureaus: Water Management Bureau, Water Rights Bureau, Adjudication Bureau, State Water Projects Bureau and the Water Operations Bureau.
The 2003 Legislature attached the Flathead Basin Commission to the department for administrative purposes. The Commission is charged to protect the natural resources and environment of the Flathead Basin.
The Water Resources Division records consist of a small sampling of the Water Resources Division’s ( 1938-1971 ) survey books of various water related projects around the state, including dams, ditches, reservoirs, city water supplies, and pumping projects. The books contain statistical information charts and notes regarding project areas, such as ditch topographies, fence and post and road locations for water related projects.
Arrangement is by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Water resources; Water survey report; Dams – Montana
Montana; Water and Water Rights
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Project Files
  - Project # 663: Hedges Ditch – Transit Notes, Vol. 6, undated (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Project #663: Daley Ditches – RCD, Vol. 28, Book 1, 1970 November (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Project #709: Lake Mary Ronan – Canal, Vol. 7, 1951 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Project #744: Woods Gulch Canal - Meagher Co. #1, Vol. 1, undated (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Project #650: Laureal – Vol. 1, Book 9, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Project - Test Holes: Billings Bench, Grandview Subdivision, BL and I Canal, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Project: Billings Bench Water Survey – Master Index, undated (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Project #663: Daley Ditches, Hedge Canal – Vol. 31, 1971 September (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Project #622: West Fork of Milk River – Vol. 2, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Project #670: Dry Creek Reservoir, Sun River Project, Vol. 44, 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Project #615: Billings Bench – Book 2, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Project #528: Smokey Butte Storage – Vol. 2, 1956 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Project #605: Main and North Canal – Vol. 11, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Project #224: Burnt Fork Dam Project – Vol. 4, 1960 September (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Project: Skalkaho Creek, 1933 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Project #766: Star Meadows Dam Site – Vol. 2, 1966 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Project #651: Sunset Valley - Vol. 1, 1942 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Project #244: North Sanders – Vol. 1, 1935 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Project #650: Vol 19, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Project #607-625: Reef Reservoir Site – Vol.12, No. 2, 1939 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Project #650: Vol 20-23, 1940 (Box-folder 1 / 22-25)